2001太空漫游
先生到了 请上主甲板
Here you are, sir. Main level, please.
好的 回程时再见
Right. See you on the way back.
再见 再见
-Bye. -Bye.
先生 早安 -早安
-Good morning, sir. -Morning.
你已经有好久没到这儿来了 -很高兴再见到你
-We haven't seen you for a long time. -Nice to see you again.
这次飞行愉快吗? 很好 谢谢
-Did you have a pleasant flight? -Very nice.
我想基地室的米勒先生 应该在等我
Mr. Miller of Station Security is supposed to meet me.
我帮你叫他好吗?-麻烦你  他来了
-May I call him for you? -Would you? Here he is!
博士你好 抱歉我迟到了
-Hello, Dr. Floyd. -Hello, Miller.
没关系 你看来气色不错
-Sorry I'm late. -That's all right.
谢谢 真高兴你回来
It's nice to have you back.
这次旅途愉快吗? -很好
-Did you have a good flight? -Very nice.
那就好 我们进去好吗? 请使用17号门
-Shall we go through? -Would you please use number 17?
谢谢你 透纳小姐
Thank you, Miss Turner.
请走这边
This way.
欢迎接受声影测试
Welcome to Voice Print Identification.
当你看见红灯亮时 请按顺序说出：
When you see the red light go on, please state in the following order:
你的目的地 国籍、还有你的全名
Your destination, your nationality and your full name.
先说姓 然后是名字和缩写
Surname first, Christian name, and initial.
月球、美国籍 佛洛伊德.赫伍德.R
Moon. American. Floyd, Heywood R.
谢谢 你已通过声影测试
Thank you. You are cleared through Voice Print Identification.
谢谢
Thank you.
我有空吃早餐吗? 也许可以
-Have I got time for breakfast? -I think we can manage that.
我还有多久出发?
How long have I got?
大概一小时十分钟
Your flight leaves in an hour and 10 minutes.
事实上 我已替你订了位
I've reserved a table for you in the Earthlight Room.
上次你来是七、八个月前吧
It's been 7 or 8 months since you were here, hasn't it?
我想想看 是去年六月 对 有八个月了
Let's see. Yeah, about 8 months.
我想你已看过新单位的工作
I suppose you saw the work on the new section?
是很不错的吗?  -不错
-Coming along great, huh? -Yeah, it's fine.
等一等!
Oh, wait!
我想打通电话 你先到餐厅 我去找你
I've got to make a couple calls. I'll meet you in the restaurant.
-哈喽 -嗯
-Hello. -Yes.
-哈罗 宝贝 -嗯
-Hiya, squirt! -All right.
你在做什么?
What are you doing?
我在玩
Playing.
妈妈呢?
Where's Mummy?
上街买东西
Gone to shopping.
那谁照顾你 -瑞契儿
-Who's taking care of you? -Rachel.
我跟她讲话好吗?-她去洗手间了
-May I speak to Rachel, please? -She's gone to the bathroom.
明天你能来参加我的派对吗
Are you coming to my party tomorrow?
抱歉 甜心 我不能去
I'm sorry, sweetheart, but I can't.
为什么
Why not?
你知道 爸爸正在旅行
Well, you know, Daddy's traveling.
很抱歉 我真的不能去
Very sorry about it, but I just can't.
可是我可以送你一个礼物
I'm going to send you a very nice present, though.
好吧
All right.
你想要什么特别的东西吗?有的
-Anything special that you want? -Yes.
什么东西?
What?
电话
A telephone.
我们已经通有很多电话了
We've got lots of telephones already.
你能不能想想其它的东西 来庆祝你的生日
Can't you think of anything else for your birthday? Something special?
有啊! 什么东西?
-Yes. -What?
一只猩猩
A bush baby.
一只猩猩? 那我们得想想办法找找看
A bush baby? We'll have to see about that.
甜心 我要你转告妈咪 你要记得?
I want you to tell Mummy something for me. Will you remember?
我会
Yeah.
你告诉妈咪我打过电话 好吗?
Tell Mummy that I telephoned. Okay?
告诉她 明天我会再打电话 好吗?
And that I'll try to telephone again tomorrow.
你会告诉她吧?
Now, will you tell her that?
我会的 很好 甜心 明天生日好好玩
-Yeah. -Okay, sweetheart. Have a nice birthday tomorrow.
好
All right.
明天生日派对愉快
And have a nice birthday party tomorrow too, huh?
好
All right.
好了 要小心 要乖乖 好吗?
Take care and be a good girl, won't you?
好的 再见
All right. Bye-bye!
再见 生日快乐
Bye-bye! Happy birthday!
电话费$1.70
（俄语）
艾琳娜 真高兴见到你 赫伍德 真高兴在此见到你
-Elena, how nice to see you again. -Heywood, what a wonderful surprise!
你看起来很不错 谢谢 你看起来也很不错
-You're looking wonderful. -You're looking well too.
这是我的好朋友 佛博士
This is my friend, Dr. Heywood Floyd.
我来介绍一下 卡莉娜博士
I'd like you to meet Dr. Kalinan.
你好 史博士 你好
Dr. Stretyneva.
这位是史麦斯洛夫博士
And this is Dr. Andrei Smyslov.
你好 久仰大名
How do you do? I've heard a lot about you.
请坐
Do sit down.
我们 不用客气 请
-Well, we-- -No, no, please.
谢谢
Thank you.
博士要喝点什么?不用 谢谢你
-Would you like a drink, Doctor? -No, thank you.
其实我还没吃早餐呢 我约了人在餐厅见面
I haven't had breakfast yet. Someone's meeting me in the restaurant.
如果各位不介意 我坐几分钟就走
I'll just sit with you a moment. Then I'll be off.
真的不喝点什么吗? 不客气 谢谢你
-Are you quite sure? -Quite sure, thank you.
葛雷哥近来如何? 他很好
-Well, how's Gregor? -He's fine.
他在波罗的海从事海底实验
He's been doing underwater research in the Baltic...
所以最近我们很少碰面
...so I'm afraid we don't see very much of each other these days.
如果见到他 记着代我问好 当然
-When you see him, give him my regards. -Yes, of course.
你们大伙要去那里? 上还是下
Well, where are you all off to? Up or down?
我们正准备回家
We're going home.
我们刚花了三个月的时间 校正柴林科号上的新天线
We've just spent 3 months calibrating the new antenna at Tchalinko.
你呢? 我正要去克莱威斯
-What about you? -I'm on my way to Clavius.
噢 是吗?
Oh, are you?
克莱威斯
Clavius.
博士 请不要介意我太好奇
Dr. Floyd, I hope you don't think I'm being too inquisitive...
但是也许你可以澄清一下 到底那里发生了什么事
...but perhaps you can clear up the big mystery about what is going on there.
我恐怕不太了解你的意思
I'm afraid I don't know what you mean.
过去两个星期 克莱威斯发生怪事
For the past two weeks...
...some extremely odd things have been happening at Clavius.
真的吗?真的
-Oh, really? -Yes, yes.
例如 当你打电话到该基地时 只能听到电话录音
For one thing, when you phone the base, all you get is a recording...
重覆的告诉你线路故障
...which repeats that the phone lines are temporarily out of order.
可能是他们的装备故障
Probably having some trouble with their equipment.
是的 起先我们也是这么想 但是到现在为止已经十天了
That's what we thought at first, but it's been going on now for 10 days.
你是说在过去十天中 你们无法与任何人联络
You haven't been able to contact anyone for 10 days?
正是如此
That's right.
原来如此
Oh, I see.
还有一件事 两天前我们有一辆火箭巴士
There's another thing. Two days ago, one of our rocket buses...
被拒绝在克莱威斯紧急迫降
...was denied permission for an emergency landing.
那就真的有些奇怪了
That does sound odd.
是的 恐怕这件事将会引起争执
I'm afraid there's going to be a bit of a row about it.
拒绝迫降是违反 国际航空暨太空协定
Denying the men permission to land violates the IAS Convention.
是的 那当然 机员们都平安归来了吗?
Yes, of course. Did the crew get back all right?
是的 是的 很庆幸 是的 很高兴听到这样
-Fortunately, they did. -Well, I'm glad about that.
佛博士对你不愿讨论的问题 一再追问 也许有些冒犯
At the risk of pressing you on a point you seem reticent to discuss...
但是我可不可以 直接的问你一个问题
...may I ask you a straightforward question?
当然可以
Well, certainly.
坦白说 我们有可靠的情报指出
Frankly, we have had some very reliable intelligence reports that...
在克莱威斯发生一种 不明来源 十分严重的传染病
...quite a serious epidemic has broken out at Clavius.
Something, apparently, of an unknown origin.
这应该就是事情的真相吧?
Is this, in fact, what has happened?
很抱歉 史麦斯博士
I'm sorry, Dr. Smyslov, but...
我无法与你讨论这件事
...I'm really not at liberty to discuss this.
这点我了解
I understand.
但是这个传染病可能 很容易就传染到我们的基地
But this epidemic could easily spread to our base.
我们必须要知道事情的真相
We should be given all the facts.
我知道
Yes, I know.
不过我已说过 我无法讨论这个问题
As I said, I'm not at liberty to discuss it.
你确定不改变主意来一杯吗
Won't you change your mind about that drink?
确定 现在我真的必须走了
No, I'm positive. I really must be going.
希望你和你太太能一起参加 六月举行的国际航空会议
I hope you and your wife come to the IAC Conference.
我们会想办法 希望届时能前来参加
I hope we can make it.
假如你们能来 记得宝贝女儿一起带来
If you do, bring that darling little daughter with you.
那要看学校假期而定
That'll depend on school vacations and all that sort of thing.
如果可以 一定带来
If we can, we will.
不要忘记不论何时 到美国来一定要来找我
You've got an invitation if you ever get to the States.
当然 葛雷哥和我 都期待着去看你们
Gregor and I will look forward to seeing you.
好了 艾琳娜 再见
Goodbye, Elena.
很荣幸见到你们 史麦斯洛夫博士
It's been a pleasure meeting you all. Dr. Smyslov.
佛博士 不管你是什么理由 去克莱威斯 祝你幸运
Whatever the reasons for your visit, the very best of luck to you.
谢谢你们
Thank you.
各位女士
Ladies.
（俄语）
零重力厕所 乘客使用前应先阅读说明
对不起 赫伍森博士 我拍完了
Excuse me, Dr. Halvorsen. I'm through now.
谢谢各位 不客气
-Thank you very much, gentlemen. -You're welcome.
我知道 大家和我一样都非常高兴
Well...
...I know you will all want to join with me...
欢迎我们杰出的朋友和同事
...in welcoming our distinguished friend and colleague...
来自国家太空航行委员会 赫伍德、佛洛伊德博士
...from the National Council of Astronautics, Dr. Heywood Floyd.
佛博士今天特别来到 克莱威斯参加我们的工作
Dr. Floyd has come up specially to Clavius to be with us today.
在简报前 我想他一定很乐意说几句话
Before the briefing, he'd like to have a few words with you.
佛博士
Dr. Floyd?
谢谢赫伍森博士
Thank you, Dr. Halvorsen.
大家好 很高兴回来和大家在一起
Hi, everybody. Nice to be back with you.
首先我带来豪尔博士的口信
First, I bring a personal message from Dr. Howell...
他对各位所作的牺牲 表示由衷的感激
...who has asked me to convey his deep appreciation...
...for the many sacrifices you've had to make.
同时他对各位在科学史上 最有意义的发现 表示祝贺
And, of course, his congratulations on your discovery...
...which may prove to be among the most significant in the history of science.
现在. .
Now...
我知道关于这件事是否保密 你们曾有不同的看法
...I know there have been some conflicting views...
...regarding the need for complete security in this matter.
说得更明白点 基地上有传染病的传说 就是这样产生的
More specifically, your opposition to the cover story...
...created to give the impression of an epidemic at the base.
我了解这和原则有所违背
I understand that beyond it being a matter of principle...
你们大家都深受其困扰
...many of you are troubled by the concern and anxiety...
担心传染病的谣言 会使地球上的亲友感到焦虑
...this story of an epidemic might cause to your relatives and friends on Earth.
我完全同情持反对意见者
I completely sympathize with your negative views.
我自己也深受谣言困扰
I find this cover story personally embarrassing, myself.
然而 我仍坚持要绝对保密
However, I accept the need for absolute secrecy in this.
我希望你们也同样赞成
And I hope you will too.
我相信大家都很清楚
I'm sure you're all aware of the grave potential...
如果在没适当准备下公布此事
...for cultural shock and social disorientation...
...contained in this situation...
对文化的冲激及 社会产生迷惑的可能性
...if the facts were prematurely made public...
...without adequate preparation and conditioning.
无论如何
Anyway...
这是委员会的意思
...this is the view of the Council.
我来此的目的 正是搜集事实与意见
The purpose of my visit is to gather additional facts and opinions...
以便草拟报告向委员会建议 何时及如何公布这件事情
...on the situation...
...and to prepare a report to the Council...
以便草拟报告向委员会建议 何时及如何公布这件事情
...recommending when and how the news should eventually be announced.
如果哪位提供我意见和看法 如果你愿意私底下也可以
If any of you would like to give me your views and opinions...
我将很高兴将它写进报告
...in private, if you like, I will be happy to include them in my report.
好了 我想这件事到此为止 有无问题?
Well, I think that's about it.
有无问题?
Any questions?
佛博士 这件事究竟要保密多久?
Dr. Floyd, have you any idea how much longer...
...this cover story will have to be maintained?
我不知道 比尔
I don't know, Bill.
我想保密时间的长短 需由委员会视状况而定
I suppose for as long as deemed necessary by the Council.
当然 在决定公布前 要有足够的时间做全盘研究
There must be adequate time for a full study...
...before any thought can be given to making a public announcement.
对了 你们当中有人已知道 委员会已正式要求
As some of you know, the Council has requested...
任何知道此事的人 都必须保密
...that security oaths be obtained in writing...
...from everyone who has knowledge of this event.
还有问题吗?
Were there any more questions?
我确定我们大家都想 尽可能和佛博士合作
I'm sure we all want to cooperate with Dr. Floyd as fully as possible...
似乎没什么问题了 我想接下来应该开始简报
...and as there are no more questions, we ought to get on with the briefing.
谢谢你佛博士 谢谢
-Thank you, Dr. Floyd. -Thank you.
有人饿了吗?
Anybody hungry?
有什么好吃的?你们说呢?
-What've we got? -You name it.
这是什么?鸡肉吗? 类似鸡的东西
-Is this chicken? -Something like that.
不管怎么样 尝尝看
Tastes the same, anyway.
有火腿吗?
Got any ham?
火腿 火腿 火腿
Ham, ham, ham....
有 在这
There, that's it.
看起来不错
Look pretty good.
他们随时都在改进
They're getting better at it all the time.
你的演讲非常棒 赫伍德 -的确如此
-That was an excellent speech. -It certainly was.
我相信他能提高全体的士气
I'm sure it beefed up morale a lot.
谢谢你 雷夫
Thanks, Ralph.
我认为你们也表现的非常好
By the way, you've both done a wonderful job.
我很欣赏你们处理的方法
I admire how you've handled this.
这样做是我们的职责
It's our job to do this thing the way you want it done.
很高兴能达到这个要求
We're only too happy to be able to oblige.
你看过这些吗?
Have you seen these yet?
整个事件就是从这里开始
-Have a look. -Here's what started the whole thing.
噢耶
Oh, yeah.
当初我们发现它时 以为是个磁性岩石的外壳
When we found it, we thought it might be magnetic rock...
但是所有地质学上的 检验都与此相反
...but all the geological evidence was against it.
甚至没有一个如此 巨大的镍铁陨石能产生 这样强烈的磁场
And not even a nickel-iron meteorite could produce a field this intense.
所以我们决定去看看
So we decided to have a look.
我们认为是某种 被埋葬建筑物较上层部份
We thought it was part of a buried structure...
所以把四周挖掘开 很不幸没有任何的发现
...so we excavated out, but we didn't find anything else.
所有的证据似乎完全确定
And the evidence seems pretty conclusive that...
它不是被自然的侵蚀或其它力量所掩盖
...it hasn't been covered by erosion or other forces.
它似乎是经过谨慎埋葬的
It's been deliberately buried.
谨慎的埋葬
Deliberately buried.
来点咖啡如何?
How about a little coffee?
太棒了 好主意
-Great. -Good idea.
我想你们也猜不出那是什么
I don't suppose you have any idea what the damn thing is?
我希望我们知道
I wish to hell we did.
唯一可以确定的是 那是四百万年前所埋的
The only thing we're sure of is it was buried 4 million years ago.
我应该说 你们确实是有重大的发现
Well, I must say, you guys have certainly come up with something.
看着点 很烫
Watch this, now. It's hot.
木星任务18个月后
晚安
Good evening.
三星期前 美国太空船发现者一号
Three weeks ago, the American spacecraft Discovery One...
开始全程五亿里的木星航行
...left on its half-billion mile voyage to Jupiter.
写下人类首次 到达这遥远行星的企图
This marked the first manned attempt to reach this distant planet.
今天下午 世界今夜节目访问了
This afternoon, The World Tonight recorded an interview...
远离地球八千万里 发现者号的机员
...with the crew at a distance of 80 million miles from Earth.
我们的话要传到太空船 需要七分钟的时间
It took 7 minutes for our words to reach the giant spacecraft...
不过这项时差已予以修正
...but this time delay has been edited from this recording.
记者马丁艾默对机员们谈话
Our reporter Martin Amer speaks to the crew.
发现者一号的机员包括五个人
The crew of Discovery One consists of five men...
和一套最新的H.A.L 9000型电脑系统
...and one of the latest generation of the HAL 9000 computers.
五人中有三人 是在太空船上睡觉
Three of the men were put aboard asleep...
说得更精确些 是保持在冬眠的状态
...or to be more precise, in a state of hibernation:
他们就是查理亨特博士 杰克金波博士 以及维克多克明斯博士
Dr. Charles Hunter, Dr. Jack Kimball and Dr. Victor Kaminsky.
下面就是我们和 任务指挥官大卫鲍曼博士
We spoke with mission commander, Dr. David Bowman...
和副指挥官 富兰克普理博士的谈话
...and his deputy, Dr. Frank Poole.
二位午安 一切都好吗?
Good afternoon, gentlemen. How is everything going?
太神奇了
Marvelous.
我们毫无怨尤
We have no complaints.
很高兴听到这句话 我想全世界的人
I'm glad to hear that. I'm sure the entire world...
都和我一样祝福你们 有个平安成功的航行
...joins me in wishing you a safe, successful voyage.
非常感谢 谢谢你们
-Thanks very much. -Thank you.
虽然冬眠 在过去太空任务中曾使用过
Although hibernation has been used on previous space efforts...
但这是第一次在出发前 将人员置于冬眠状态
...this is the first time men were put into hibernation before departure.
为什么要这么做呢?
Why was this done?
这样做的目的 在使我们的生命支持能力
This was done to achieve the maximum conservation...
基本的食物与空气 得到最大量的保存
...of our life-support capabilities, basically food and air.
现在冬眠的机员代表测量组
The three hibernating crew members represent the survey team.
他们的专长要等到我们 快接近木星时才会用到
Their efforts won't be utilized until we approach Jupiter.
普里博士 冬眠时究竟像什么样子
Dr. Poole, what's it like while you're in hibernation?
完全像睡着般没有知觉
It's exactly like being asleep. You have no sense of time.
唯一不同的是不会做梦
The only difference is that you don't dream.
据我所知 你一分钟呼吸一次 真的吗?
As I understand it, you only breathe once a minute. Is this true?
那是真的 心跳一分钟三次
Right, and the heart beats three times a minute.
体温降至约摄氏三度
Body temperature is usually down to about three degrees centigrade.
发现者的第六位机员 并不担心冬眠的问题
The sixth member of the crew was not concerned...
...about the problems of hibernation...
因为他是科技智慧最新结晶
...for he was the latest result in machine intelligence:
HAL系统 9000型电脑 它能够复制...
The HAL 9000 computer, which can reproduce...
虽然有些专家 仍喜欢使用“模拟”一辞
...though some experts prefer to use the word "mimic"...
...大部份人脑的活动
...most of the activities of the human brain...
并具有无法计算的 较大速度与可靠性
...and with incalculably greater speed and reliability.
下面我们将与这部电脑谈话
We next spoke with the HAL 9000 computer...
我们知道他有个名字叫赫尔
...whom, we learned, one addresses as "Hal. "
午安 赫尔 一切都好吗?
Hello, Hal. How's everything going?
午安 艾默先生 一切都非常顺利
Good afternoon, Mr. Amer. Everything is going extremely well.
赫尔 在这次任务中 你有一大堆的责任
Hal, you have an enormous responsibility on this mission...
每个任务责任都很重要
...perhaps the greatest of any single mission element.
你是这艘太空船的首脑和中央神经系统
You're the brain and nervous system of the ship.
你的责任包括监视人们冬眠
Your responsibilities include watching over the men in hibernation.
对这样的任务 你是否会缺乏信心
Does this ever cause you any lack of confidence?
艾默先生 让我这样说
Let me put it this way, Mr. Amer.
这套9000型系统的电脑是目前最可靠的电脑
The 9000 Series is the most reliable computer ever made.
9000型系统的电脑 从来没有出现过错误 或是不实的资料
No 9000 computer has ever made a mistake or distorted information.
我们使用实用的定义 极为简单绝不可能产生错误
We are all, by any practical definition of the words...
...foolproof and incapable of error.
赫尔 不管你智慧多高 仍得依靠人们执行
Hal, despite your enormous intellect, are you ever frustrated...
你是否因此会产生挫折感
...by your dependence on people to carry out actions?
一点都不会
Not in the slightest bit.
我很高兴和人们一起工作
I enjoy working with people.
我和普里博士、鲍曼博士 有着非常良好的关系
I have a stimulating relationship with Dr. Poole and Dr. Bowman.
我的任务范围 包括整个太空船的作业
My mission responsibilities range over the entire operation of the ship...
所以我非常忙碌
...so I am constantly occupied.
我把自己使用到最大程度
I am putting myself to the fullest possible use...
我想那是任何有责任感的人 所希望做到的
...which is all, I think, that any conscious entity can ever hope to do.
普里博士 一年中大部份时间 都和赫尔一起生活
Dr. Poole, what's it like living for most of the year...
感觉如何?
...in such close proximity with Hal?
是的 我和他非常的接近
It's like what you said earlier.
他正像是第六位机员
He's like a sixth member of the crew.
由于他会说话 你会很快的调整你的观念
You quickly get adjusted to the idea that he talks, and think of him...
当你对电脑讲话时 会认为他真是另一个人
...really just as another person.
你会有一种感觉 那就是 他能够作情绪上的反应
In talking to the computer, one gets the sense that he's capable...
...of emotional responses.
例如：当我问到他的能力时
When I asked him about his abilities...
我可以感受到他非常自负 自己精确完整的能力
...I sensed pride in his answer about his accuracy and perfection.
你相信赫尔真有感情吗?
Do you believe that Hal has genuine emotions?
是的 他表现得很有情感
Well, he acts like he has genuine emotions.
当然 他就是这样设计 使我们更容易对他说话
He's programmed that way to make it easier for us to talk to him.
至于他是否真有情感
As to whether or not he has feelings...
我想是没有人可以回答的
...is something I don't think anyone can truthfully answer.
对不起 富兰克
Excuse me, Frank.
什么事?赫尔
What is it, Hal?
我刚接到你父母的电讯
We've got the transmission from your parents coming in.
好的
Fine.
请接过来 把我移过去一点 好吗?
Put it on here, please. Take me in a bit.
当然可以
Certainly.
哈罗 富兰克 亲爱的 祝你生日快乐
Happy birthday, darling!
祝你生日快乐 万事如意
Happy birthday. Many happy returns.
请稍为高一点
A bit higher, Hal.
我和你妈妈都感觉很好
Mother and I are both feeling wonderful.
瑞和莎莉本来也要来此
Ray and Sally were going to be here...
但是瑞的背痛又发作了
...but Ray's back went bad on him again.
-你喜欢这个生日蛋糕吗? -看起来很不错 是不是?
-How do you like your cake, dear? -It's great, doesn't it?
可惜你不能与我们共享
Sorry you can't join us.
对了 前几天碰到鲍伯
I ran into Bob the other day.
他要我代他祝你生日快乐
He said to wish you happy birthday.
我所有的学生也虔诚祝福你
All my students send their best wishes too.
你知道他们整天都在谈论你
They talk about you all the time.
你是二年级的大名人
You're a big celebrity in the second grade.
你知道吗? 上星期我们还上电视呢!
We were on TV last week.
你母亲和我 还有大卫父母都接受访问
Your mom and I and Dave's parents were asked...
问我们对于杰出儿子的感受
...what we thought of our illustrious son.
你可以想像得到 我们告诉他们什么吗?我想可能在下星期四播出
Imagine what we told them. It's being broadcast next Thursday.
也许你可以收到
Perhaps you can listen in.
关于艾拉莲和比尔的消息 我们也感到激动 亲爱的
We're thrilled about Elaine and Bill.
我很高兴买礼物送你 但请告诉我可以花多少钱
I'll be glad to get the gift, but tell me how much to spend.
对了 富兰克 关于你的薪水
Oh, Frank, about your AGS- 19 payments...
我想我帮你处理好了
...I think I straightened it out.
昨天我和会计室的人谈过
I talked to the accounting office yesterday...
你下个月就可领到较高薪水
...and they said you'd be receiving your higher rates of pay by next month.
我想不出还有什么要说
I can't think of anything else to say.
代我们向大卫问好 记得代我们向他致意
-Give our love to Dave. -Be sure to give him our best regards.
祝你有个最愉快的生日
We wish you the very happiest of birthdays.
生日快乐
All the best, son.
祝你生日快乐
Happy birthday to you.
祝亲爱的富兰克生日快乐
Happy birthday, dear Frank
祝你生日快乐
Happy birthday to you.
下星期三再见
See you next Wednesday.
富兰克 生日快乐
Happy birthday, Frank.
谢谢你赫尔 请将椅子调低
Thank you, Hal. A bit flatter, please.
皇后吃卒
Anyway, queen takes pawn.
主教吃骑士的卒
Bishop takes knight's pawn.
这步如何?
Lousy move.
好 城堡进一步到国王
Rook to king one.
富兰克 抱歉我想你输了
I'm sorry, Frank. I think you missed it.
女王进三到主教 主教吃女王 骑士吃主教
Queen to bishop three. Bishop takes queen.
将军!
Knight takes bishop. Mate.
看起来好像你对
Looks like you're right. I resign.
谢谢你 这盘棋下得很愉快
Thank you for a very enjoyable game.
彼此彼此
Thank you.
大卫 晚安 赫尔 一切都好吗?
-Good evening. -How are you, Hal?
一切都好 你呢? 还不错
-Everything's running smoothly. You? -Not too bad.
你有没有做些别的事 只画了几张素描
-Have you been doing more work? -A few sketches.
可以让我看看吗?当然可以
-May I see them? -Sure.
大卫 你画得很不错
That's a very nice rendering, Dave.
我认为你有很大进步
I think you've improved a great deal.
请你再拿近一点好吗?当然可以
-Can you hold it a bit closer? -Sure.
那不是亨利博士吗? 是的
That's Dr. Hunter, isn't it?
问你一个私人问题 不介意吧?
By the way...
...do you mind if I ask you a personal question?
一点也不介意
No, not at all.
请原谅我的好奇 但在过去的几星期中
Well, forgive me for being so inquisitive...
我怀疑你们对这次任务 是否另有想法
...but lately I've wondered...
...whether you might be having second thoughts about the mission?
这是什么意思
How do you mean?
这很难解释
Well, it's rather difficult to define.
也许只是我对此事的关心
Perhaps I'm just projecting my own concern about it.
你知道对于和这次任务 有关的一切怪事
I know I've never completely freed myself of the suspicion...
我的疑心从未完全解除
...that there are some extremely odd things about this mission.
我想你多少同意我的看法
I'm sure you'll agree there's some truth in what I say.
我不知道 那是个相当难以回答的问题
That's a rather difficult question to answer.
大卫 讨论这件事你不介意吗?
You don't mind talking about it, do you, Dave?
不 一点都不介意
No, not at all.
相信大家在出发前都听过 在我们四周流传的一些谣言
Certainly no one could have been unaware of the very...
...strange stories floating around before we left.
有关于月球上 有某样东西被挖掘出来的谣言
Rumors about something being dug up on the moon.
我从不相信这些谣言
I never gave these stories much credence...
但就某些已发生的事来说
...but particularly in view of some other things that have happened...
我发现很难把他们忘掉
...I find them difficult to put out of my mind.
例如说
For instance...
我们的装备是如此安全周密
...the way all our preparations were kept under such tight security.
亨利博士、金波博士 和克明斯基博士
And the melodramatic touch of putting Drs. Hunter...
在各别训练四个月后
...Kimball, and Kaminsky aboard...
以非常戏剧性的手法 在冬眠状态下登上太空船
...already in hibernation, after four months of training on their own.
你是为了心理报告而问的?
You working up your crew psychology report?
当然是的
Of course I am.
很抱歉问你这件事 我知道有点可笑
Sorry about this. I know it's a bit silly.
等等
Just a moment.
我刚在AE35单位中 找到一项故障
I've just picked up a fault in the AE-35 unit.
在72小时内它将完全失效
It's going to go 100 percent failure within 72 hours.
到现在为止 仍在你的作业极限内吗?
-Is it still within operational limits? -Yes.
它会保持现状直到完全失效
And it will stay that way until it fails.
我们还有72小时可以修护?
We have 72 hours till failure?
是的 这个数字完全可靠
Yes. That's a completely reliable figure.
看样子我们必须把它拿进来 不过我得先和富兰克商量
Then we'll bring it in. I'll go over it with Frank...
然后再与任务控制中心联络 请复印一份资料给我
...and get on to Mission Control. Let me have the hard copy on it.
X光一号 这是任务中心
X-ray delta one, this is Mission Control.
你的2013讯息收到了
Roger your two-zero-one-three.
抱歉 伙伴们 目前有点小麻烦
Sorry you fellows are having a bit of trouble.
我们正在观察 任务模拟器上的电传资料
We're reviewing telemetric information in our simulator and will advise.
罗杰 你准备前往EVA 在AE35失效前加以更换
Roger your plan to go EVA and replace alpha-echo-3-5 unit...
...prior to failure.
请准备辅助舱前往EVA
Prepare B-pod for EVA, Hal.
请打开舱门 赫尔
Open the pod doors, Hal.
赫尔 真该死 就是找不到一点毛病
I'm damned if I can find anything wrong with it.
是啊
Yes...
真是令人费解
...it's puzzling.
我以前从来没见过这样的事
I don't think I've ever seen anything quite like this before.
我建议我们把它放回去
I would recommend...
继续运作到失效为止
...that we put the unit back in operation and let it fail.
这样可很简单的追查出原因
It should then be a simple matter to track down the cause.
我们可以承受暂时停止通信 以便更换它
We can certainly afford to be out of communication...
...for the short time it will take to replace it.
X光一号 这是控制中心
X-ray delta one, this is Mission Control.
你的1930讯息收到了
Roger your one-niner-three-zero.
我们同意你的计划 更换一号单位以检查错误
We concur with your plan to replace unit to check fault prediction.
同时必须告诉你们 我们初步调查发现
We advise you that our preliminary findings...
你们船上的三倍九零电脑 失效预测功能有问题
...indicate that your onboard 9000 computer...
...is in error predicting the fault.
重覆一次 失效预测功能有问题
I say again, in error predicting the fault.
我知道这听起来不太可能 不过这个结论是根据...
I know this sounds rather incredible, but this conclusion is based on...
三倍九零电脑计算出来的
...the results from our twin 9000 computer.
我们自己也感到怀疑 我们正在做横向的例行检查
We're skeptical, and we're running cross-checking routines...
...to determine reliability of this conclusion.
对这个故障感到抱歉 各位
Sorry about this little snag.
只要我们一查出结果 便会马上通知你们
We'll get this info to you as soon as we work it out.
X光一号 这是任务中心
X-ray delta one, this is Mission Control.
2091讯息传送完毕
Two-zero-four-nine. Transmission concluded.
我希望你们两人 对这件事不要操心
I hope the two of you are not concerned about this.
不 我并不操心
No, I'm not, Hal.
真的吗?
Are you quite sure?
真的 不过我倒想问你一个问题 当然可以
-Yeah. I'd like to ask you a question. -Of course.
你认为你和成套9000 电脑间有何矛冒
How do you account for the discrepancy between you and the twin 9000?
我不认为有什么问题
Well, I don't think there is any question about it.
这只能归咎于人为的错误
It can only be attributable to human error.
这类错误以前也发生过
This sort of thing has cropped up before...
而且总是由于人为的疏忽
...and it has always been due to human error.
听我说 赫尔
Listen, Hal...
9000型电脑 从来没有出错的例子吗?
...there's never been any instance at all...
...of a computer error occurring in a 9000 Series, has there?
从没有 富兰克
None whatsoever, Frank.
9000型电脑有完美的记录
The 9000 Series has a perfect operational record.
当然 我知道 9000型电脑的伟大成就
I know the wonderful achievements of the 9000 Series, but....
但你确定即使最小的错误 都不曾发生过吗?
Are you certain there's never been even the most insignificant computer error?
富兰克 从没有
None whatsoever, Frank.
老实说 对这件事我自己并不担心
Quite honestly, I wouldn't worry myself about that.
好了 赫尔 我的确相信
Well, I'm sure you're right, Hal.
你是对的 非常谢谢你
Fine. Thanks very much.
法兰克 C舱的送话器有点小毛病
I'm having trouble with my transmitter in C-pod.
你能不能和我一同检查?
Would you come down and take a look at it with me?
赫尔 回头见
See you later, Hal.
赫尔 请转动C舱
Rotate C-pod, please, Hal.
大卫 你发现什么毛病
What sort of trouble are you having?
我在D频道中收到一些干扰
I've been getting some interference in D-channel.
我们去看看
We'll have a look at it.
赫尔 请开门
Open the door, Hal.
请转动备用舱 赫尔
Rotate pod, please, Hal.
停住备用舱
Stop pod rotation, please, Hal.
请转动备用舱 赫尔
Rotate the pod, please, Hal.
我想他听不到我们的谈话
I don't think he can hear us.
请转动备用舱 赫尔
Rotate the pod, please, Hal!
是的 的确没问题了
Yeah, I'm sure we're okay.
你认为如何?
What do you think?
我不确定 你呢?我觉得它不太对劲
-I'm not sure. What do you think? -I've got a bad feeling about him.
是吗? 是的
-You do? -Yeah. Definitely.
你说不是吗?
Don't you?
我不知道 我想是的
I don't know. I think so.
你知道他说得没错 9000型电脑有完美的记录
He's right about the 9000 Series having a perfect operational record.
确实
They do.
那听起来似乎有点 像著名的末世之言
Unfortunately, that sounds a little like famous last words.
但他不正是以这种观念 对失效作方式上的分析
Still, it was his idea to carry out the failure mode analysis.
他的确显示出 他的诚实与自信
It certainly indicates his integrity and self-confidence.
假如他是错的话 这倒是最好的证明方法
If he were wrong that would prove it.
假如他知道他是错的话
It would be if he knew he was wrong.
我是搞不清楚 但我感到有些奇怪
I can't put my finger on it, but I sense something strange about him.
没有不把一号单位 放回去的更好理由
There's no reason not to put back the unit and...
继续失效上的分析 -我同意
-...carry on with the failure analysis. -No, no, I agree about that.
好的 那就试看看
Let's get on with it.
好吧 但是大卫
Okay. But, look, Dave.
如果 我们把这个机件放回去 它并未失效
Say we put the unit back and it doesn't fail?
赫尔岂不是很没面子
That would pretty well wrap it up as far as Hal is concerned.
那我将会有 非常严重的麻烦不是吗?
-We'd be in very serious trouble. -We would, wouldn't we?
我们能做什么呢?
What the hell can we do?
我们不可能有太多选择 我不认为我们有任何选择
-We wouldn't have too many alternatives. -We wouldn't have any alternatives.
在这船上没有那一部份 不是在他控制下
Every aspect of ship operations is under his control.
If he's malfunctioning...
除了关机 我想不出别的方法
...I don't see any choice but disconnection.
我同意你的看法
I'm afraid I agree with you.
也没有其他的看法
There'd be nothing else to do.
这真有点捉弄人 是的
It'd be a bit tricky.
我们必须切断它的主脑功能
We'd have to cut his higher brain functions...
而不干扰自动调节系统
...without disturbing the purely automatic and regulatory systems.
同时必须在地面电脑控制下 维持传送程序以继续任务
We'd have to work out the details...
...of continuing under ground-based computer control.
是的 看来这种方法 比让赫尔继续控制安全多了
Yeah. That's far safer than allowing Hal to continue to run things.
我刚想到另一件事
Another thing just occurred to me.
九千型电脑从没有被关机过
No 9000 computer has ever been disconnected.
是啊 九千型电脑 过去也没有失误过
No 9000 computer has ever fouled up.
那倒不是我的意思
That's not what I mean.
我不知道 他对此事的想法如何?
I'm not so sure what he'd think about it.
中断
赫尔 请开辅助舱通道门
Prepare G-pod for EVA, Hal.
无线电联络上他了吗?
Any contact with him yet?
不行 还是无法联络
The radio is still dead.
你检查过了吗?我检查过了
-Do you have a positive track on him? -I have a good track.
你知道发生什么事 赫尔?
Do you know what happened?
大卫 抱歉 我的资讯不足
I'm sorry, Dave. I don't have enough information.
赫尔 请开辅助舱通道门
Open the pod door, Hal.
电脑失效
生命功能情况危急
生命功能结束
赫尔 请开辅助舱通道门
Open the pod bay doors, please, Hal.
赫尔 你听得见我说话吗
Hello, Hal, do you read me?
Do you read me, Hal?
赫尔 你听得见吗
Hello, Hal, do you read me?
听得见吗 赫尔
Do you read me, Hal?
我听得见 大卫 我听得见你说话
Affirmative, Dave. I read you.
请开辅助舱通道门
Open the pod bay doors, Hal.
我恐怕不能这样做
I'm sorry, Dave. I'm afraid I can't do that.
有什么问题吗?
What's the problem?
我想你知道问题所在 就像我现在所做一样
I think you know what the problem is just as well as I do.
赫尔 你在说什么?
What are you talking about, Hal?
这次任务对我太重要了 不能让你破坏
This mission is too important for me to allow you to jeopardize it.
我不懂你在说什么 赫尔
I don't know what you're talking about, Hal.
我知道你们计划将我关机
I know that you and Frank were planning to disconnect me...
那是我不允许发生的事
...and that's something I cannot allow to happen.
赫尔 你怎会有这种 该死的想法
Where did you get that idea, Hal?
大卫 虽然你采取了 非常彻底的防范
Although you took very thorough precautions in the pod...
让我听不见
...against my hearing you...
但是我会读唇语
...I could see your lips move.
好的 赫尔
All right, Hal.
我从紧急阻隔门进去
I'll go in through the emergency air lock.
大卫 没有太空盔
Without your space helmet, Dave...
你会发现那是相当困难
...you're going to find that rather difficult.
我不想再和你辩论 赫尔
Hal, I won't argue with you anymore.
请开门吧!
Open the doors!
大卫
Dave...
这段谈话 不能达到任何目的 再见
...this conversation can serve no purpose anymore. Goodbye.
赫尔
Hal?
你以为你在做什么 大卫?
Just what do you think you're doing, Dave?
大卫
Dave...
我认为我该给你一个答案
...I really think I'm entitled to an answer to that question.
我知道我最近不太对劲
I know everything hasn't been quite right with me...
但我可以很有信心的保证
...but I can assure you now...
...very confidently...
将会再度好起来
...that it's going to be all right again.
我现在觉得好多了
I feel much better now.
我真的觉得好多了
I really do.
听我说 大卫
Look, Dave...
我可以了解你的愤怒
...I can see you're really upset about this.
我认为你应冷静的坐下来
I honestly think you ought to sit down calmly...
吃片镇静剂 好好的想想看
...take a stress pill and think things over.
我知道 最近我曾经 作了一些很差劲的决定
I know I've made some very poor decisions recently...
但我可以完全向你保证
...but I can give you my complete assurance...
我的工作将回复正常
...that my work will be back to normal.
对这次任务 我们具有最大的信心和热忱
I've still got the greatest enthusiasm and confidence in the mission...
同时我很想要帮助你
...and I want to help you.
大卫
Dave...
停手
...stop.
停下来 行么
Stop, will you?
停下来 大卫
Stop, Dave.
请你停止好吗?大卫
Will you stop, Dave?
大卫 停手
Stop, Dave.
我害怕
I'm afraid.
大卫 我害怕
I'm afraid, Dave.
我的智力正在消失
My mind is going.
我可以感觉到
I can feel it.
我的智力正在消失
My mind is going.
这是毫无疑问的
There is no question about it.
我可以感觉到
I can feel it.
我害怕
I'm...
...afraid.
午安
Good afternoon...
各位先生
...gentlemen.
我是赫尔 九千型电脑
I am a HAL 9000 computer.
我开始操作是在伊利诺州
I became operational...
...at the HAL plant...
威尔巴拉的HAL工厂
...in Urbana, Illinois...
时间是1992年1月12日
...on the 12th of January, 1992.
我的老师是蓝利先生
My instructor was Mr. Langley...
他教我唱过一首歌
...and he taught me to sing a song.
如果你喜欢听
If you'd like to hear it...
我可以为你唱
...I can sing it for you.
是的 赫尔 我喜欢听
Yes, I'd like to hear it, Hal.
你就为我唱吧
Sing it for me.
歌名叫“黛西”
It's called "Daisy. "
#　Daisy　#
#　Give me your answer, do　#
#　I'm half...　#
#　...crazy　#
#　All for the love of you　#
#　It won't be a stylish marriage　#
#　I can't afford a carriage　#
#　But you'll look sweet　#
#　Upon the seat　#
#　Of a bicycle built for two　#
各位先生 午安
Good day, gentlemen.
这是一卷预录的简报资料
This is a prerecorded briefing...
在你们出发前制作的
...made prior to your departure...
为了高度重要的保密理由
...and which, for security reasons of the highest importance...
在任务中 只有太空船上的 九千型电脑知道事情真相
...has been known on board during the mission...
...only by your HAL 9000 computer.
你们现在是在木星的太空中
Now that you are in Jupiter's space...
全部船员均已苏醒
...and the entire crew is revived...
现在真相可以公布了
...it can be told to you.
十八个月前在地球以外
Eighteen months ago...
发现了第一个 有生命才智的证据
...the first evidence of intelligent life off the Earth...
...was discovered.
被埋藏在月球表面四十尺下
It was buried 40 feet below the lunar surface...
靠近克拉科火山口
...near the crater Tycho.
除了一个非常强有力的
Except for a single, very powerful...
放射性发光体对准木星外
...radio emission aimed at Jupiter...
这四百万年高龄的黑岩石 仍旧保持完全无生命状态
...the 4-million-year-old monolith has remained completely inert...
它的根源与目的
...its origin and purpose...
至今仍是一个谜
...still a total mystery.
木星以及无限穹苍
谢谢观赏